Finding Aid for Casa de Unidad records, 1980-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Casa de Unidad records 1980-2006
Casa de Unidad (Detroit, Mich.)
2009121 Bd 2; Bd Outsize
The records of the Casa de Unidad Cultural Arts and Media Center cover the organization’s efforts to promote, develop, and celebrate Hispanic and Latino arts and traditions in Southwest Detroit. The record group consists primarily of correspondence, board minutes, grant proposals and reports, newsletters, event and program budgets, event flyers, educational workshop reports and audio material.
7 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated June 2009 by CLAVE, the Community of Latino Artists, Visionaries, and Educators (donor no. 10201 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Casa de Unidad Cultural Arts and Media Center was founded in December of 1980. In November of 1981, the organization was officially incorporated by the State of Michigan. Throughout the 1980s, 1990s, and early 2000s, the center devoted its resources to identifying, developing and preserving the Hispanic/Latino cultural heritage of Southwest Detroit. Among the programs offered by Casa de Unidad were educational workshops in the visual, literary, and performing arts. The center also sponsored a workshop designed especially for high school students entitled Tradiciones Vivas.
Besides cultivating local interest in the arts, the center nurtured many local artists by providing an exhibition space in the Galería, the center's art gallery. Casa de Unidad also complied the first Michigan Hispanic Arts Directory in 1988-1989. Moreover, the center held an annual two-day performing arts festival called Unity in the Community, which brought together local businesses, human service agencies, artists and entertainers for a weekend of cultural unity and celebration.
One of Casa de Unidad's most significant contributions to the preservation of local cultural history came out of their 1987 documentation project, which resulted in the published study Tradiciones del Pueblo: Traditions of Three Mexican Feast Days in Southwest Detroit (1990). The study was based on a series of oral histories and interviews from Detroit Latinos about the community's artistic and cultural traditions, such as Posadas, Fiestas Gaudalupanas, and Día de los Muertos.
The records of Casa de Unidad cover the period between 1980 and 2006. The collection consists primarily of correspondence, board minutes, grant proposals and reports, newsletters, event and program budgets, event flyers, educational workshop reports and audio material. The majority of the material is in English, though a small number of flyers, newsletters, and audio recordings are in Spanish. The collection contains the following series: Administrative Material, Educational/Artistic Activities, Unity in the Community Festival, and Audio Material.
Subjects:
Casa de Unidad (Detroit, Mich.); Hispanic American art--Michigan.; Hispanic American artists--Michigan--Detroit.; Hispanic Americans--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Casa de Unidad (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--History.; Hispanic Americans--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre Terms:
Compact discs.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Administrative Material
  Administrative Material series documents Casa de Unidad's history, organizational structure, expenses and contributions. The series contains written accounts of the organization's history, its mission statement, and its by-laws and constitution. The series also contains the organization's financial statements and budgets, board minutes, grant proposals and reports, as well as multiple volumes from Casa de Unidad's bilingual newsletter "El Barrio."
  - Background/History 1980-2001, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Pre-History 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - By-laws and constitution undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1981-1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1995-2005, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors 1994-2004 (Box 1)
  - Board Meeting minutes and notes 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Board Minutes Notebooks
    - 1994 (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996 (Box 1)
    - 1997 (Box 1)
    - 1998 (Box 1)
    - 1999 (Box 1)
    - 2000 (Box 1)
    - 2001 (Box 1)
  - Membership Committee 1981 (Box 1)
  - Steering and communications committee 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Strategic Plan Material 1995-2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan Council for the Arts, correspondence and reports 1982-1995, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Neighborhood Opportunity Fund, correspondence and reports 2000-2006, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - City of Detroit Planning and Development Department 1993-2001, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Arts Strata 1988 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Latino Arts Initiative 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Presbyterian Sisters of Charity, funding proposals 1983 (Box 2)
  - Campaign for Human Development, funding proposal 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Report on Community Development Block Grant 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Financial Reports and Budgets 1983-1987 (Box 2)
  - Indirect Cost Proposals 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Financial Comparative Statements 1994-2002, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Independent Audit 1993-1996 (Box 2)
  - Hispanos Unidos and Casa de Unidad Lease 1982-1984 (Box 2)
  - El Barrio, background/miscellaneous material (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Newsletters 1981, 1985, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter Printing Equipment and Technique 1983 (Box 2)
- Educational/Artistic Activities
  Educational/Artistic Activities series reflects Casa de Unidad's commitment to promoting, developing and celebrating Hispanic and Latino arts in Southwest Detroit. The series is separated into four subseries: Tradiciones Vivas, Workshops, Other Activities, and Artist Files.
  - Tradiciones Vivas
    Subseries Tradiciones Vivas contains material related to Casa de Unidad's art and humanities workshop for high school students. The subseries includes the workshop's budget, outgoing correspondence, program evaluations, and photographs.
    - General 1995-1996, 2002, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Project Overview 2000 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1995-2004 (Box 3)
    - Announcements and Flyers 1995-2002 (Box 3)
    - Budget 1998-2005 (Box 3)
    - Grant Agreements and Reports 1995-2002 (Box 3)
    - Summer Dreams Grant 1993, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Rules and Expectations 1995-2001 (Box 3)
    - Evaluations and Reports 1995-1996, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Evaluation Notebook 2003 (Box 3)
    - Project Notebook 1995-1999, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Curriculum 2003, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Photographs undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Workshops
    Subseries Workshops documents the diverse offering of extracurricular programs offered by Casa de Unidad. The material in the Workshops subseries includes project reports from each class meeting as well as workshop syllabi.
    - Announcements 1986-1990 (Box 3)
    - Listings and Dates 1987-2004 (Box 3)
    - Performance Schedules 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Monthly Performance Report 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Workshop Miscellaneous undated (Box 3)
    - Creative Writing Workshop 1989 (Box 3)
    - Graphics Workshop 1985-1989 (Box 3)
    - Journalism Workshop 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Offset printing and camera workshop 1986-1989, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Photography Workshop 1981-1989, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Printing Workshop by the Human Press undated (Box 4)
    - Writing workshop 1982-1988 (Box 4)
  - Other Activities
    Subseries Other Activities underscores the organization's significant contribution to the cultural development of the Detroit Latino community. Much of the material in the subseries is event announcements and flyers, with the majority related to exhibits from the Galería, the center's art gallery. However, the subseries also contains the Michigan Hispanic Arts Directory of 1988-1989, 1989-1990, and 1990-1993. The 1988-1989 Hispanic Art Directory was the first of its kind complied in Michigan. Also included in the subseries is Tradiciones del Pueblo, a published study based on a series of oral histories and interviews from Detroit Latinos about the community's artistic and cultural traditions.
    - Event Announcements, general 1984-2001, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Event Posters 1988-2002 (Folder 1)
    - Cinco de Mayo 1993-2002, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Día de los Muertos 1989-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Galería (flyers, news releases) 1986-2002, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Michigan Hispanic Arts Directory 1988-1990, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Machito Memorial Concert 1988, 2 folders; 1 oversize folders (Box 4)
    - "Moving Our Barrio Forward," mini convention 1981 (Box 4)
    - Tito Puente Dinner 1984 (Box 4)
    - Tradiciones del Pueblo: Traditions of Three Mexican Feast Days in Southwest Detroit, 1990, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Youth Festival 1985 (Box 4)
    - "La onda Latina en Poesia," poetry anthology 1985 (Box 4)
    - "She Be Me" Exhibit 1998 (Box 4)
    - "Through Their Eyes" Photo Exhibit 1992 (Box 4)
    - "Zorra," a theatrical production 1983 (Box 4)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 4)
  - Artist Files
    Subseries Artist Files contains files kept by Casa de Unidad on a variety of Michigan based artists. Many of the artists on file exhibited their work at the organization's Galería. The material is arranged alphabetically according to the artists' name, and primarily contains the artist's resume, biographical material, and flyers from upcoming exhibitions or events.
    - Alva, Diana (Box 4)
    - Basombrio, Isabela (Box 4)
    - Bustos, Graciela (Box 4)
    - Cardenas, Brenda (Box 4)
    - Cardona, Ana (Box 4)
    - Cox, Kenn (Box 4)
    - Cruz, Benny (Box 4)
    - Damiano, Linda (Box 4)
    - De la Torre, Lucia (Box 4)
    - De la Vega, Ruben (Box 4)
    - Delano, Jack (Box 4)
    - Diaz, Carlos (Box 4)
    - Duran, Ismael (Box 4)
    - Esteves, Sandra Maria (Box 4)
    - Figueroa, Encarnita (Box 4)
    - Gomez, Jose Antonio (Box 5)
    - Gonzalez-Gonzalez Alberto (Box 5)
    - Harrison, Wendell (Box 5)
    - Hernandez, Lolita (Box 5)
    - House, Gloria (Box 5)
    - Jurado, Alvaro (Box 5)
    - Lara, Rene (Box 5)
    - Lara, Lupe (Box 5)
    - Luevanos, Mary (Box 5)
    - Mad Hatters (Box 5)
    - Mendoza, Nora Chapa (Box 5)
    - Mora, Francisco (Box 5)
    - Munoz, Delfin (Box 5)
    - Narezo, Jose Luis (Box 5)
    - Negrete, Jesus "Chuy" (Box 5)
    - Nethercott, Shaun (Box 5)
    - Ochoa, David (Box 5)
    - Perea, Florencio (Box 5)
    - Perez, Hector Tapia (Box 5)
    - Perez Prades, Danis (Box 5)
    - Quiroz, Martin (Box 5)
    - Reagen Rosales, Christine (Box 5)
    - Reyes, Arnoldo (Box 5)
    - Rivera, Osvaldo (Box 5)
    - Rodriguez, Maria Elena (Box 5)
    - Rosado S, Theresa (Box 5)
    - Rosas, Mel (Box 5)
    - Saenz, Gil (Box 5)
    - Sanchez, Jacqueline (Box 5)
    - Sanchez, Trinidad (Box 5)
    - Sarmiento, Alexia (Box 5)
    - Sovoda, Gladys (Box 5)
    - Sun Messengers (Box 5)
    - Tiznado, Dulce Maria (Box 5)
    - Vargas, George (Box 5)
    - Villalobos, Alma Rosa (Box 5)
- Unity in the Community Festival
  Unity in the Community Festival series contains material from Casa de Unidad's annual two-day festival celebrating the cultural diversity of Southwest Detroit and showcasing the commercial districts and human service agencies in the community. The series contains correspondence with various local community organizations, event budgets and corporate grants/sponsorship, and publicity material such as newspaper clippings and flyers.
  - Annual Festival
    - 3rd 1981 (Box 5)
    - 4th 1982 (Box 5)
    - 5th 1983 (Box 5)
    - 6th 1984 (Box 5)
    - 7th 1985 (Box 5)
    - 8th 1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 9th 1987 (Box 5)
    - 10th 1988, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 11th 1989, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 12th 1990 (Box 6)
    - 13th 1991 (Box 6)
    - 14th 1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 15th 1993 (Box 6)
    - 16th 1994, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 17th 1995, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 18th 1996 (Box 6)
    - 19th 1997 (Box 6)
    - 20th 1998 (Box 6)
    - 21st 1999 (Box 6)
    - 22nd
      - General 2000, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Event Binder 2000, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 23rd
      - General 2001, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Event Binder 2001, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - 24th 2002 (Box 7)
    - 25th
      - General 2003, 2 folders (Box 7)
        (includes 3 compact discs storing images)
      - Event Binder #1 2003 (Box 7)
      - Event Binder #2 2003, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Event Binder #3 2003, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 26th 2004 (Box 7)
- Audio Material
  Audio Material series contains 31 cassette tapes. Cassette tapes 1 through 10 are a part of Casa de Unidad's efforts to document the cultural legacy of the Detroit Latino community through a series of oral histories and interviews with individuals who settled in Detroit during the 1920s. Other recordings include lectures presented at Casa de Unidad, recordings of cultural events, and board meetings.
  - Oral History
    - Father James Barrett, part 1 April 12, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 1)
    - Father James Barrett, part 2 April 12, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 2)
    - Maria Benitez, interviewed on subject of Fiestas de la Fe, part 1 May 4, 1991 (Box 7)
      (in Spanish)
      (Cassette Tape 3)
    - Maria Benitez, interviewed on subject of Dia de los Muertos, part 2 May 4, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 4)
    - Angel Cornejo May 17, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 5)
    - Nick Mares, Jr., part 1 May 29, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 6)
    - Nick Mares, Jr., part 2 May 29, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 7)
    - Joe Rodriguez, part 1 June 21, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 8)
    - Joe Rodriguez, part 2 June 21, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 9)
    - Joe Rodriguez, part 3 June 21, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 10)
  - Michigan Latino Arts and Cultural Initiative
    - Grand Rapids, part 1 and 2 August 12, 1999 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 11)
    - Grand Rapids, part 3 and 4 August 12, 1999 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 12)
    - Grand Rapids, part 5 August 12, 1999 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 13)
    - Saginaw, part 1 and 2 August 14, 1999 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 14)
    - Saginaw, part 3 August 14, 1999 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 15)
  - Casa de Unidad Board Meeting January 12, 2000 (Box 7)
    (Cassette Tape 16)
  - Religious Fiestas of Southwest Detroit undated (Box 7)
    (Cassette Tape 17)
  - Lectures
    - Laurie Sommers on collecting Oral Histories undated (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 18)
    - Juan Herrera (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 19)
    - Dave Perry, Photography Documentary October 15, 1988 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 20)
    - Ana Cardona on Gerontology Perspective, Sue Perez on Images, and John Cicala on Folklorist October 15, 1988 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 21)
    - Dolores Gonzalez October 15, 1988 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 22)
  - Lupe Aguirre Tribute
    - Gracious a la Vida May, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 23)
    - Gracious a la Vida May, 1991 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 24)
  - Unity in the Community Festival September 13, 1992 (Box 7)
    (Cassette Tape 25)
  - Tradiciones del Pueblo slide presentation
    - Part 1 undated (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 26
    - Part 2 undated (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 27)
  - Fiestas Guadalupanas
    - St. Anne's December 11, 1989 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 28)
    - St. Anne's December 11, 1989 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 29)
    - St. Anne's December 11, 1989 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 30)
    - St. Gabriel's December 10, 1989 (Box 7)
      (Cassette Tape 31)